The topic of this conference is "fintech" (financial technology), but Bitcoin is not "fintech."
本次会议的主题是“金融” （金融技术），但比特币不是“金融”
That may surprise many of you. I hope, as you learn more about Bitcoin, you will continue to be surprised.
这可能会让你们中的许多人感到惊讶。我希望，随着您对比特币的了解越来越多，您将继续惊讶下去
I'll start [this talk] with what Bitcoin isn't.
我将以"比特币不是什么"开始[这个话题]。
Bitcoin isn't a company. Bitcoin isn't an application. Bitcoin isn't "fintech." Bitcoin isn't banking.
比特币不是公司。比特币不是应用程序。 比特币不是“金融科技”。比特币不是银行业务
Bitcoin is a protocol, an internet system. It does not belong to any one company.
比特币是一个协议，一个互联网系统。 它不属于任何一家公司
It doesn't belong to any one organization, just like the internet doesn't belong to any company.
它不属于任何一个组织， 就像互联网不属于任何公司一样
It is a system for conducting transactions and commerce on a global basis,
它是一个与全球贸易进行交易的系统
[along with] many other trusted applications.
[以及]许多其他受信任的应用程序
Bitcoin isn't what you expect. Bitcoin changes our expectations of what money is.
比特币不是您想的那样， 比特币改变了我们对货币的预期
It changes the foundation of how money and payment systems work.
它改变了基础货币和支付系统运作的基础
This isn't just a little [disruption] that will affect a few companies. This [will be] a [big disruption].
这不仅仅是会影响[干扰]几家公司 这[将]是[大颠覆]
It will be as big as the internet, perhaps in some ways even bigger.
它的影响将和互联网一样大， 也许在某些方面甚至更大
It will not just affect finance. It will also affect politics and governance. It will affect societies as a whole.
这不仅会影响金融。这也会影响政治 它会影响整个社会
I'm a technical person, so I'm interested in how Bitcoin works. After five years, I still discover new things...
我是技术人员，所以我对比特币的运作方式很感兴趣，五年过去了，我仍然都在每天发现新事物...
and understanding it in even great depth.
并深入了解它
Let me start with something that happened two weeks ago.
让我从发生在两个星期前的事情说起
Two weeks ago, president Barack Obama stood up on stage at South by Southwest (SXSW) conference.
两周前，美国总统巴拉克·奥巴马站在South by Southwest（SXSW）的会议舞台上
He talked about surveillance and said, "If [law enforcement] can't unlock the phones,
他谈到了监控，并说， “如果（执法部门）无法解锁手机，
that is if every person is carrying a Swiss bank account in their pocket."
那意味着，每个人都在 他们的口袋里带着一个瑞士银行帐户。”
This [example] was supposed to provide a view of a terrifying future where everyone has privacy.
这个[例子]为未来每个人的隐私保护提供了一个可怕的未来
Now, I'm sure some people in this room might think that is not such a bad idea...
我相信在坐的有些人 可能认为这不是一个坏主意...
for everybody to have a Swiss bank account in their pocket.  [Laughter]
每个人都有一个瑞士银行 放在他们的口袋里。 [笑声]
You see, [the American] president was wrong.
你看，[美国]总统错了
There won't be a future in which everyone has a Swiss bank account in their pocket.
未来不会人人口袋里有一个瑞士银行帐户
[It is a] present [and future] in which everyone can have an entire Swiss bank in their pocket.
而是在现在[和未来]，每个人的口袋里可以拥有整个瑞士银行
I have a system in my back pocket that can generate two billion "account numbers,"
我的后兜里有一个系统 可以产生20亿个“帐号”，
and wire money anywhere in the world [in minutes or even seconds].
在世界任何地方都可以汇款 [以分钟甚至几秒为单位]
It can be the point of origination for loans and mortgages, for international finance and trade.
它可以成为贷款和抵押，国际金融和贸易的起点
[It can be used for] import-export business, or for a remittance business.
[可用于]进出口业务， 或汇款业务
I can build novel financial applications and trading instruments, install them on my phone,
我可以安装新颖的财务应用程序， 交易工具，将它们安装在我的手机上，
I have mobile banking, not as a customer, but as a banker.
我有一个手机银行，不是作为客户，而是作为银行家
Even if you unlock my phone, my "Swiss bank account in my pocket" [could still be] secure.
即使您解锁我的手机，我的“口袋里的瑞士银行帐户” [仍然]安全
The terrifying future of privacy that president Obama sees is actually already part of our present.
奥巴马总统看到的隐私的可怕未来 实际上已经是我们现在的一部分
On January 3rd 2009, the world changed.
2009年1月3日，世界发生了变化
Few people noticed that [someone had] invented a system of money that allows...
很少有人注意到[某人] 发明了一种允许...
everyone in the world to have financial privacy, security, and [powerful] capabilities.
世界上每个人都拥有隐私，安全和[强大]功能的金融工具
That will have important implications throughout [the rest of our] history.
这将在[我们将来]的历史中产生重要的影响
People [often] ask me, "Will Bitcoin one day become the currency of a country? Will it be adopted by the banks?"
人们[经常]问我，“比特币有一天会成为 一个国家的货币吗？银行会采用吗？”
To ask that question is to miss the point. Bitcoin is not a national currency.
这个问题提错了， 比特币不是国家货币
Bitcoin is now the de facto currency of the internet.
比特币现在是互联网上的事实货币
We have already seen more than a thousand other similar [cryptocurrencies].
我们已经看到了不止一个 上千种其他类似的[加密货币]
[Bitcoin] is not just a new system of [payments], but a network-centric system of money.
[比特币]不只是一种新的[支付]系统， 它是以网络为中心的货币体系
The major change with Bitcoin is not simply that we can 'email' money across the world,
比特币的主要变化不只是简单的 我们可以在全球范围内“通过电子邮件发送”资金，
but that we can change the organizational structure behind money from hierarchical...
而是我们可以改变组织 改变等级制背后的货币结构...
to a flat, network-centric model.
变成扁平化，以网络为中心的模型
This is the same type of model that changed centralized publishing and [media] broadcasting...
这种模式曾改变了集中出版行业和[媒体]广播行业...
into a [more distributed], networked communication system of the internet.
变成一个[更分散的]互联网通信系统
It brought us social media; now we will have social banking one day, a system that is person-to-person.
它带给我们社交媒体； 我们总有一个会有个人对个人的社会银行
[There is a] need for disintermediation. There will be [less] need for financial intermediaries.
这[需要]去中介化， 对金融中介机构的需求将减少
The role of intermediaries in most transactions is not necessary when you can transact directly.
当您可以直接进行交易时， 在大多数交易中中介的角色是不必要的
That doesn't mean people who use bitcoin won't have intermediaries, but they don't [need them like today].
这并不意味着使用比特币的人将没有中间人，但他们不需要[像今天一样]
They can choose to add a third-party into their transactions, or they can choose not to.
他们可以选择将第三方添加到 他们的交易，或者他们可以选择不这样做
This is the choice that [becomes available] when you have this new currency of the internet.
当您拥有这种新的互联网货币时，这将会是可选的
It brings with it so many implications.
它带来了很多含义
On my flight into Zürich, I flew with Swissair, in an aircraft with a flag painted on its tail.
在飞往苏黎世的航班上，我乘坐的是瑞士航空的航班， 在飞机的尾巴上绘有国旗
What an anachronism that is. Swissair is owned by Lufthansa. It is no longer a national carrier.
这已经过时了。瑞士航空为汉莎航空所有；它不再是国家航空公司
But I remember a time when every aircraft had a flag on its tail, when every airline was a national airline...
但我记得有一段时间，每架飞机的尾部都有国旗，当时，每家航空公司都是一家国家航空公司...
that had exclusive and monopoly access to the skies and airports of [their] countries.
这些国家具有到[他们]国家的天空和机场的独占和垄断访问权
I remember a time when phone companies had flags and belonged exclusively to countries.
我记得曾经电话公司都带有国旗
Those anachronisms are gone.
那些时代错误已经一去不复返了
The idea that, in a few decades, money will still have a flag or queen on it, and belong to a single nation,
几十年后，货币上仍然会有国旗或女王， 并且属于一个国家，
will also seem like a silly anachronism.
也似乎是一个愚蠢的时代错误
It won't go away completely, of course. There will still be national money.
当然，它不会完全消失。 仍然会有国家货币
But there will also be hundreds, possibly thousands of [cryptocurrencies] that have no flag, no allegiance...
但是也会有数百甚至数千 没有标志，没有效忠对象的[加密货币] ...
to any country.
在任何一个国家
More importantly, money that is neutral to geopolitics.
更重要的是，对地缘政治而言中立的货币
There is enormous power in a system of money that is neutral to geopolitics;
在一个对地缘政治中立的货币体系中， 存在着巨大的力量
a system of money that [is regulated by] mathematical functions which can be inspected by everyone,
[由]数学控制的货币体系， 每个人都可以检查它
and doesn't change its nature according to the latest alliances or hostilities between nations.
也不会根据国家之间的最新联盟或敌对行动而改变其性质
A money that remains a stable and neutral backdrop to global trade.
对全球贸易来演，美元仍是一个稳定而中立的背景
A money of the internet, for the internet, and by the internet.
互联网货币， 生于互联网，用于互联网
That can sound quite terrifying, honestly.
老实说，这听起来很可怕
If you're terrified, you are probably also worried about how the internet [enabled] free expression for everyone.
如果害怕，您可能还会担心互联网如何让每个人都能自由表达
But I can tell you, there is a generation growing up right now who, when they hear of a money that is...
但我可以告诉你，现在有一代人正在成长，当他们听到货币是...
of the internet, for the internet, and by the internet, think it is a natural [progression] and how it should be.
生于互联网，用于互联网， 他们会认为这是自然的[进步]，理应如此
The internet has been giving them freedom [of expression] for as long as they remember.
互联网给了他们[表达]自由 ，只要他们记得
By the time the next generation reaches the age of 16 and finally acquires the right to open a bank account.,
到下一代达到16岁时， 最终获得开设银行帐户的权利
they may have been using digital, network-centric currencies like bitcoin already for a decade.
他们可能一直在使用以网络为中心的数字货币，比如像比特币这样的货币已经有十年了
Two-year-olds, six-year-olds can open a Bitcoin [wallet]. You don't open an account.
不管是两岁、还是六岁的孩子都可以拥有一个比特币[钱包]。不需要开设帐户
You can download an app.
只需要下载一个应用程序
After a decade of using digital money on the internet that is near instantaneous and global,
十年来，互联网上的 数字货币交易几乎是即时的、全球性的
when happens [when those kids] go and open [their] first bank account?
那些孩子去开设他们的第一个银行帐户的时候
[They] have a conversation [with a teller], who explains why the system only operates from Monday to Friday.
[他们] [与柜员]交谈，由他解释 为什么系统仅在星期一至星期五运行
Why does it take three to five business days to execute an international transaction?
为什么执行国际交易需要三到五个工作日？
Given that they have loaned money to the bank, why will they be charged five Swiss francs a month...
既然他们已经向银行借钱了， 为什么每月要向他们收取五瑞士法郎...
for the privilege of [having a bank account that earns] no interest?
为了[拥有一个不赚钱的银行账户]的特权？
[In the future], when you explain [banks] to a 16-year-old,
[将来]，当您向16岁的孩子讲解[银行]时，
they will look at you as if you have just asked them to send the fax. [Laughter]
他们会不解的看着你，好像你刚刚要求他们发送传真。 [笑声]
The world has changed, but this is not something to be afraid of.
世界已经改变，但这并不可怕
This is a tremendous opportunity.
这是一个巨大的机会
There are 2.5 billion people in the world who have no economic access to banking,
世界上有25亿人没有渠道拥有银行服务
according to The World Bank, which is a very conservative estimate.
根据世界银行， 这是一个非常保守的估计
They only count the heads of household...
这还是他们只算户主的结果......
and the circumstances in which no banking is available whatsoever,
在没有银行的情况下
those who are entirely in cash-based societies.
那些完全依赖现金的人
That is a very conservative [way] to estimate it. I look at it from a different perspective.
那是一种非常保守的估计方法， 让我从另一个角度来看待它
I belong to a privileged elite who can open an online brokerage account within twenty-four hours.
我属于一个享有特权的精英阶层， 可以在二十四小时内开立一个经纪账户
Tomorrow morning, I can be trading in yen on the Tokyo stock exchange.
明天早上，我可以在东京证券交易所以日元交易结算
I can wire money anywhere in the world, in any currency I want. I have the full capability of international, liquid,
我可以根据需要以任何货币在世界任何地方汇款。我的银行服务具备国际金融的流动性
multi-currency banking with no currency controls.
没有限制的多币种业务服务
How many people have that? Maybe 1.5 billion people.
有多少这样的人？也许有15亿人。
Then there is the other six billion, many of them completely unbanked, most of them under-banked.
还有另外60亿人，其中许多人完全没有银行存款，其中大多数没有多少银行存款
From a technological perspective, giving them economic inclusion is now within our reach.
从技术角度来看，让他们享有普惠金融是我们现在力所能及的事情
But we lack the political [will] to do that. We have decided that it is more important...
但是我们缺乏这样做的政治意愿 我们认为下面的事情更重要...
to live in a world where every financial transaction, [from anywhere and from anyone], should be fully identified.
生活在这样一个世界里， [任何地方和任何人]的一笔金融交易都应完全被标识
We have created a system where [we as] individuals have no privacy,
我们创建了一个系统，在这个系统中 [我们]个人没有隐私权，
where every financial transaction is subject to total surveillance,
每笔金融交易受到全面监视
and you must identify yourself in order to transact.
并且您必须标识自己才能进行交易
This [kind of system] has never existed in history before.
这种制度在历史上从未存在过
The fundamental advantage of cash is that you don't need to do a credit check when you exchange it.
现金的基本优势是您不需要在 兑换时进行进行信用检查
If you give me ten Swiss francs, the money itself is the bearer of value. It is independent of your credit [score],
如果你给我十瑞士法郎，钱本身就是价值的承担者。它与您的信用[得分]无关
or your identity.
也与您的身份无关
I do not care, nor do I want to know, who you are. I can simply transact [peer-to-peer with you].
我不在乎，也不想知道你是谁。 我可以简单地与您进行面对面交易
That is a very fundamental [advantage which] allows everyone to participate in the economy.
这是一个让每个人都参与经济的非常基本的[优势]
[But politicians and some corporations] are trying to change that, where every endpoint...
[但是政治家和一些公司] 试图改变这一切，每个交易方...
is controlled and identity is part of every financial transaction.
是受控制的，身份是每笔金融交易其中的一部分
That is not a good future. That is a future which worsens economic access and equality.
那不是一个美好的未来。 那个未来恶化了经济准入和平等
That is a future in which people are no longer just cut off because they don't have sufficient documentation.
那个未来里，人们因为没有足够的证明文件而被切断和经济间的联系
[They use it to] cut off entire countries. In the era of the internet, economic inclusion is declining.
[他们用来]切断整个国家经济的发展。 在那个时代互联网的普及程度正在下降
But bitcoin brings a new model of digital cash, where identity is irrelevant and unnecessary,
但是比特币带来了一种新型的数字现金， 在身份无关紧要和不必要的地方，
where privacy is the default.
隐私是默认设置
In that model, security [is incentivised] by the network-centric money.
在这种模型中， 通过以网络为中心的资金[激励了安全性]
The instrument itself bears value. It is unassailable, unforgeable, and doesn't require identity.
该工具本身具有价值。这是无懈可击的， 不可伪造的，不需要身份证明的
With that, we will break down the biggest barrier to economic inclusion.
这样，我们将打破经济包容的最大障碍
A simple text-messaging feature phone in the middle of a village in sub-Saharan Africa, connected to a solar cell,
在撒哈拉以南非洲的一个村庄里，有一个简单的短信功能手机，连接着太阳能电池充电的手机
will have the same capabilities as a Swiss bank.
将具有与瑞士银行相同的功能
[It could] be an originating point or a destination point for international wire transfers, remittances, credit,
它可以用于国际电汇，汇款，信贷，
with a bearer instrument of value that is cash, in an electronic medium, without any concern for identity.
以现金形式的不记名票据电子媒体，无需担心身份标识
That is the vision I have. To me, it is very important to re-discover the value of individual privacy.
这就是我的愿景。对我来说， 重新发现个人隐私的价值很重要
Individual privacy is economic inclusion. That is how we have always operated as a society.
个人隐私是经济包容。 这就是我们一直作为一个社会运作的方式
The dream, [or rather nightmare], of creating a completely controlled and closed system of finance,
创建一个完全受控、封闭的金融体系的梦想 (或者更确切的说是噩梦)
where everything is under surveillance, started in the 1970s.
一切都处于监视之下，这始于1970年代
[That dream] died on January 3rd 2009 with the invention of Bitcoin. It will never happen now.
[那个噩梦]死于2009年1月3日， 由于比特币的发明。现在永远不会发生这种噩梦
Now, every person in the world has the option to trade in digital cash.
现在，世界上每个人都有进行数字现金交易的选择权
We will not bank the other six billion, but rather we will de-bank all of us.
我们不会为另外六十亿人提供银行， 相反，我们将使所有银行破产
Banking is now an app. That doesn't mean that there will be no room for banks in this.
银行现在是一个应用程序。 那不代表这样银行就没有生存空间了
Quite the contrary in fact, [there will still be a need] to coordinate lending, to deliver security services,
相反，[仍然有需要] 协调贷款，提供安全服务，
and offering other financial services [may] become even greater.
并提供其他金融服务的[可能]变得更大
The opportunity is to encompass the other six billion into this new world of application-based banking,
我们的机会是将其余的六十亿人纳入这个基于应用程序银行的新世界
to create a world in which borders are meaningless, just like they [often] are on the internet.
创建一个没有边界的世界， 就像他们[经常]上网冲浪一样
This will require some very brave bankers. You must go against an edifice of borders,
这将需要一些非常勇敢的银行家 您必须违背边界大厦，
built over the last fifty to seventy years, which have segmented the world into isolated islands of finance...
这些边界建于过去五十至七十年， 将世界分割成孤立的金融岛...
that cannot connect to each other.
无法相互连接
The promise at the end of [the road] is this:
[道路]尽头的承诺是这样的：
billions of new people, new customers who now have access to a global financial system.
数十亿新人，新客户现在可以使用全球金融系统
The era of currencies with flags is as obsolete as the era of airlines with flags.
带国旗标志的货币时代结束了， 就像带有国旗标志的航空公司时代已过时一样
We must not fear this. We must welcome the fact that this has now happened. It cannot be turned back.
我们一定不要害怕。我们必须欢迎以下事实：现在已经发生了。它不能回头
It cannot be stopped. It is already happening.
它无法停止。它已经发生了
Those who embrace it will have the opportunity to enter this new world...
那些拥抱它的人将拥有 进入这个新世界的机会...
and create financial opportunity for many.
并为许多人创造经济机会
There is a difference between banking as it is executed in America, and banking as a culture in this country.
美国的银行业和美国的银行文化是由区别的
I am very hopeful that I can bring this message here [and you will understand].
我非常希望我能在这里带来这个消息[您将理解]
In America, investment banking is where your banker smiles to your face while helping you through an IPO,
在美国，投资银行是您的银行家在帮助您完成首次公开募股时对您微笑，
yet is front-running transactions behind your back and picking your pocket. [Laughter]
然而，尚未进行前期交易 他们就会偷偷把手伸进你的口袋。 [笑声]
That is the truth.
这是事实
[In contrast], Switzerland has a centuries-old tradition of banking as a multi-generational relationship of trust.
[相较之下]，瑞士银行业有着悠久的传统， 是一种多代人之间的信任
A relationship that is as sacred as a relationship with your doctor, your lawyer, or even your priest.
一段和您的医生，律师甚至牧师一样神圣的关系
It is a relationship that aims to give individual power, wealth control, and privacy to every customer.
这种关系旨在赋予个人权力， 赋予他们财富控制和保护隐私的权利
If you really believe in that culture, if you really feel the ethos of banking is that service to your customers,
如果你真的相信那种文化，如果你真的觉得 银行的精神是为您的客户提供服务，
then perhaps you can see that bitcoin is simply a new means of delivering that relationship.
那么也许您会看到比特币仅仅是一种实现这种关系的新方法
These new network-centric digital currencies [can] deliver unassailable privacy and security.
这些新的以网络为中心的数字货币 [可以]提供无懈可击的隐私和安全性
They are a way to re-establish that ethos of private banking, but not just for the few.
它们是一种为私人银行业务重新建立这种精神的方式， 但不仅限于少数几个人
For everyone.
而是为了每一个人
That is what I hope you will see in this new post-national, international, network-centric money.
这就是我希望您会在新产品中看到的 以国家，国际，以网络为中心的资金
The money of the internet. Thank you. [Applause]
互联网的货币。谢谢。 [掌声]